<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>One argument more against the cavaliers; taken from their violation of churches. Where towards the close are subtilly disputed these two questions. 1 Whether the separatist (as he is called) who makes his house (or as it is said) his barn a church, is more scandalous or the cavalier (who looking another way in his discourse and profession) hath yet at Oxford where his Maiestie resides, turned churches (with reverence be it spoken) into prisons, and Iakes, and in Devonshire at many places into stables. 2 Whether churches thus profaned, and fallen from grace, and holinesse, are not by the bishops to be reconsecrated.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90149</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871428</idno>
  <idno type="VID">155891</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942494</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E101_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21449</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871428</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871428e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E101[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>One argument more against the cavaliers; taken from their violation of churches. Where towards the close are subtilly disputed these two questions. 1 Whether the separatist (as he is called) who makes his house (or as it is said) his barn a church, is more scandalous or the cavalier (who looking another way in his discourse and profession) hath yet at Oxford where his Maiestie resides, turned churches (with reverence be it spoken) into prisons, and Iakes, and in Devonshire at many places into stables. 2 Whether churches thus profaned, and fallen from grace, and holinesse, are not by the bishops to be reconsecrated.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare when men think what they list and speake and write what they think. [1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "London. may. 12th 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church buildings --  Vandalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155891:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155891:1"/>
            <p>ONE ARGUMENT MORE AGAINST THE CAVALIERS; TAKEN FROM THEIR VIOLATION OF CHURCHES.</p>
            <p>Where towards the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ose are subtilly Disputed These two Questions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Whether the Separatist (as he is called) who makes his house (or as it is said) his Barn a Church, is more scandalous or the Cavalier (who look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another way in his discourse and Profession) hath yet at Oxford where his Maiestie resides, turned Churches (with Reverence be it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n) into Prisons, and lakes, and in Devonshire at many places into Stables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Whether Churches thus profaned, and fallen from Grace, and Holinesse, are not by the Bishops to be Reconsecrated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare when men think what they lift and speake and write what they think.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155891:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ONE ARGUMENT MORE</hi> against the Cavaliers taken from their violation of Churches, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any of this Kingdome, have seemed of late to be much troubled, (I cannnot say in conscience, untill it better appeare by their conversations, that they make a conscience of any thing, therefore, let it be trouble in their thoughts,) and trouble others with their sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y discourses, about the throwing down of Organes, silencing of Cathedrall Roarers, and Squeakers, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of images, defaceing the Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh paint, and gaudery of Churches, and assaulting immodestly forsooth, and irreligiously, not onely that sacred smock of the whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> the Surplice, but also the formalists grand Charter for Heaven the Common Prayer booke: all this while these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout men have not been at all perplexed, or moved at that piacular insolence, and more then heathenish impiety of the Cavaliers at <hi>Oxford, Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Thames</hi> and <hi>Cirencester,</hi> have not onely made prisons, but by the in humane restraint of their Prisoners, lakes; and in <hi>Devonshire,</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi> stables of Gods houses; so reverentiall and devoutly tender of the honour of Gods houses, have these Bishops white boyes been, who yet in the account of some half witted Gulls, are the onely Patrons both of Churchmen, and Churches, and the truly zealous advancers of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion. The serious consideration of which premisses, calls to my remembrance, that no lesse true then famous axiome of Divines, <hi>quicquid propter Deum fit, aqualiter fit</hi> (1) what is done to Gods glory, is alwayes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155891:2"/> done upon the same occasions, for he that honoureth God upon true Grounds will honour him impartially, and at all opportunities alike; by the help of which substantiall ground I shall at once confute both the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the dissembling Cavalier, and also the opinions and discourses of those formall Protestan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, who upon all occasions decry the Brownist and his practice, and yet have not an ill word for these cursed Cavaliers, who farre transcend the Brownist in that very particular, whereof the Brownist in their misguided partiall judgement stand guilty.</p>
            <p>First then, if the Cavalier in good earnest dislike the rudenesse of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratist, in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying violent hands upon these sacred Utensills, appointed by our holy mother-Church, for the sett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng forth of Gods worship with more luster, and a stronger Influence upon the dull affections of the vulgar, why doth the same R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke-hell so farre forget his own discourse, as to unhallow not onely the sacred implements, but the very Churches themselves, if his eye were all on Gods glory, in his accusations of the Separatist? he might see as just cause to condemne himself, who doth the same thing in a more notorious manner, if any love to God set his tongue on work against the Separatist, it would teach his hand to abstain from that which he so deeply censures in the other.</p>
            <p>Seco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly, tell me, thou lukewarm▪ or rather key-cold Protestant, who ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alwayes snarling at these poore despised Christians, whose pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctise th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nkest thou is more scandalous, the Brownist's, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho out of conscience la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs to purge out Churches of these Babilonish Reliques, or the Cavalier (who at least without, if not against Conscience) transformes the very Churches themselves into Prisons, Stables, lakes? didst thou adore these stinking Cavaliers onely (as thou saist) for their zeal and Religion to Gods houses, then couldest thou not hold also from def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing them for their unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampled polluting of them: either then spare the lash of thy venomous tongue towards the one, or els<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> spit thy venome also at the other.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour thou knowest (if I may without offence mention that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name, when I talk of these varlets) tells us that the temple is greater, and holier then either the Altar, or gold upon the Altar, and accounts of the Scribes, and Pharisees, as of blind buzzards, who thought otherwise <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.17. If it be so then I hope the blind formalist by the same force of reason will be convinced, that the churches themselves deserve more reverence from us, then Organes or other Popish trumpery; if therefore thou hast any heart (thou besotted ignorant formalist) to put i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> practise the former golden rule above mentioned, fail not to remember that when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155891:3"/> thou disgorgest thy rancor against Separatists for dishonouring Gods house, thou oughtest at the same time to bespatter the Cavalier, who much more dishonours it; if thou forget this thy duty inforc'd upon the same ground, then take it not amisse, if thou be herafter acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by every wise man that hears thee a shamelesse Censor; and that thou rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thy malignant humour then any judgement, when thou severely repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>st the one, and sparest the other, who more justly deserves thy bitterest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions.</p>
            <p>But notwithstanding all that hath been said, or (it may be) can be said, are there not some so impudent as to palliate and varnish ouer this cursed fact, who yet keep on barking at the poore separatist? nay are not some grave Doctors of that University, where this fact was committed who have had the fore heads not onely in their private discourses, but (I would I could not say it) in the pulpet, as it were in despight of all that which hath hitherto been preached &amp; written, by that practise to the contrary, to legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate that base action and proclaime it not onely lawfull and seemely, but laudable? and now here I beseech you upon what learned grounds these grave beasts have so determin'd it? because forsooth the Cavaliers were necessitated to what they did, wanting other convenient receptacles for their prisoners. Fye upon that foul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mouth that said it, fouler I wis then those profane Churches after a months defilement: for were there in all <hi>Oxford</hi> no unsanctified Colledges, which might with more convenience and lesse scandall have been converted into Prisons and Jakes then God houses? to my apprehension, rather then you should have so thwarted your Episcopal doctrine, by such an unheard of president at such a time, when your zeale for Churches and their ornaments should have been most conspicuous, had it not been much better, and more advantageous to your cause that your selves had wanted for a time the convenience of houses, then that Gods houses should bee so fouly dishonoured. <hi>Vobis ipsis spectantibus &amp; plauden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus,</hi> whilst your selves were lookers on, nay applauders and collourers of so shamefull an action? especially since you cannot, but have fresh in your memory, that at the reedifying of St. <hi>Pauls Church</hi> at London, good St. Gregories was demolished by the Command of your then great <hi>Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane,</hi> that so St. Pauls might have the more elbow-room, for no man hath yet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard of any other cause, whence I thus reason; If God himselfe may be cashiered of a Church meerely out of a silly complement to St. Paul, your selves might with patience have layen in the streets (a decent lodging for such Atheists) for the preseruing Gods house from such unexpiable dishonour.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155891:3"/>
            <p>Yea but another Reverend beast said that this disuse (how finely the man could phrase it) of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hese Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rches, was onely for some short time; he that said so, might as well excuse a sonne that ravisheth his Mother, by saying he did it onely for a time; can the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ggarly circumstance of time excuse that odious practise which should not so much as lodge in your thoughts, the least minute of time? Moreover the people of <hi>Oxford</hi> know for how long time this Sacriledge was continued, and how ready the same men are (should God permit them any more to conquer, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he base use of their past victories will, I doubt not, avert) to doe the like or a more impious and scandalous act at any time</p>
            <p>But it hath been gravely answered: that the Prisoners, good men had their option, at least dese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved no other place of their restraint then Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Had these Cay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fs knowne so much, they had questionlesse found prisons some where else; least in any thing these poore Saints should by their meanes have had their desi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es; againe these poore men though they most of all love Gods houses, yet know, that to love them for such uses, had been to have loved the abuses of them which were not to love them.</p>
            <p>Another incarnate Divell said aloud, that such Puritans deserved in that house to be punisht, where by their precisenes they had so often offended; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch is all one as if he had said, they deserve there to be punished, where God had been by them so devoutly serv'd. What reward waites for thee thou Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh tongue? <hi>similis labra luctucas,</hi> a blasphemy well beseeming a Court divine; neverthelesse the truth is, what ever pretences they have sought out for the palliating this unparalel'd piece of Atheisme, for so it would have been accounted three yeares since, even by the whole rabble of these Cathedrall Sycophants, the true cause I say of this vile fact was none other then the base esteeme (however they have seem'd to carry it) that party hath of Churches: of which as formerly they speak with reverence, and entered them with great shew of devotion, and at other mens charges adorn'd, &amp; set them forth with all manner encomiums of holynes, so now the tide of things being somewhat turn'd, and Policy coming in the room of shewfull Pageant like devotions, as a more helpfull assistant to the present exigences: now I say the same men whose thoughts were wholly pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd with Popish projects of attiring Churches; there by to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to their Canterburian Idoll, are as well content that the same Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches should be profain'd by the vilest offices: Nay most confident I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, and so I beleeve are all others who have with discretion lookt into their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled outward devotions, that so their cause may be advanced by it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155891:4"/> the best of them care not, if all the Churches in England were converted into synagogues for Jewes, or Mosques for Mahomet, nay their height of joy it would be, if all our Churches were turned (as of late some of them you know have beene) into Prisons, so Puritans and Roundheads fill'd them: and if all manner of service of God were for ever laid aside upon condition the title of their Lordly revennues were chang'd from frank Almoygne to fee simple, whereby they might durably entayle their pride and luxury upon their licentious brats and posterity.</p>
            <p>Had not some such christian thoughts and desires as these, lodged in the breasts of our Court-Clergy-Parasites at <hi>Oxford,</hi> it is impossible but that upon view or notice of that Publique Profanation of their Churches, either some Arch-bishop, or Bishop or Doctor, especially that Ceremonious Master of Baliol Colledge Do. Laur. who wore the consecrated slippers, and spent most of his stock of learning upon that empty discourse of his, touching the holinesse of churches, should not have made way to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie, and after this or the like manner have eas'd his conscience, and exprest himself to his sacred person.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Most gracious Soveraigne, defender of the truly aunci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t Catholique faith, and the great protector both of Churches and Churchmen.</p>
                  <p>I humbly crave your Maiesties gracious pardon that I your Maiesties most unworthy servant, yet truly loyall subiect dare adventure to open my mouth before your sacred Maiestie, having not first received your Maiesties commands for the unloosing my infant tongue.</p>
                  <p>Your all knowing Maiestie cannot but exactly know and it hath been a subiect frequently stood upon and gravely pressed in your Maiesties audi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce, by your Maiesties most faithfull subiects and servants the Arch-bishops, Bishops and other of your learned Clergy, whose happinesse it hath been to performe their duties before your Maiestie in the house of God. That the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Churches or Temples are places set apart &amp; consecrated to Gods pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar service. That God himselfe whom the Heaven of Heavens cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, delights to dwell in these houses made with hands, vouchsafes a speciall presence unto them, and conferrs at the instance and devout importunity of his pious servants are all though ineffable holinesse upon them, and therefore in all ages of the Church, more especially in the purest times when the seemly worship of God most flourisht, a singular care hath been alwayes taken to preserve these sacred fabricks from common uses, especially from Profanation; in imitation whereof (for your divine Maiestie cannot fall short in any point of the most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Christian Princes) there is, at least hath been of late yeares under your
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155891:4"/> Maiesties most religious Raigne, the beauty of holinesse so farre forth to be found in your Maiesties Churches, that in despight of these ignorant peevish male-contents who care not or rather desire that Gods houses should be as undecently or sluttishly kept as their shops or Barnes? Churches have been to admiration adorned, Altars erected, Copes, Tapers, Crucifixes and other comely and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ornaments brought in use againe, and by your Maiesties countenance, and the vigilancie of the Reverend Fathers of your Church, the antient and soule-ravishing worship of God so setled, not onely in your Churches but also in the aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctions of your subiects, that a proportionable reward thereof in this life, the choysest blessing of Heaven surrounded your royall throne, the maligners of your Maiesties Diadem and the sacred Miter, find few, at least, no conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable advocates. Indeed it cannot be dissembl'd that of very late dayes by the mighty working of Satan, these contemptibe mushromes (but now touched at) discovering a discontented party though from different grounds from them) amongst the Nobles and Commons in the late Parliament of your Maiesties own most Gracious calling, who envying the happinesse of your Maiesties meniall servants, and some select Ministers of state, whom the beames of your Maiesties Grace had most iustly made glorious, or (which is nearest of all the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uth, lowring at your Maiesties royall scepter, &amp; Prerogative, a tribe of Politicks destitute of all deserts, or else your omniscious Maiesty had certainly taken notice of them) yet highly conceited of an indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>verable, wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ency in themselves, and a suitablenesse to high employments, which God knowes they eminently want; unto this seed of evill doers permitted by the Divine Providence in your Kingdome, onely to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise the vertues of your accomplished Councell, have this onely reserve of turbulent Cartwrights <hi>Geneva</hi> novelty applied themselves, and in requitall of their crafty simpathizing with their Rebellious ends, have been admitted into their confederacy, who so gracious with them, as these Church-racking, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous spirits, these every where unprotected, and baffled Sectarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, who again the better to gratifie their new masters, and to approve thems<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves, and (which is their meat and drink) to doe mischiefs, upon apprehensions of their new patrons designe fell speedily, and furiously (as their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is) to work, blew the coales most zealously to their Rebellious enterprise, disparaged the Crown: blemished that intaminate Peerelesse Consort, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inferiour to that greatest saint of her name in heaven, but immortality, threw dirt in abundance upon the sacred Miter, buzzed impure notions of license▪ and independency into the credulous vulgar, in a word so plaid their parts in scurrilous libells, Sermons, discourses, that in short time, they which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155891:5"/> set them a work had nothing almost <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for themselves to doe, but onely to admire the dexteritie and successefullnesse of these formerly contemned instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Whereupon their new masters abundantly sensible of their sufficiency began to unfold themselves more freely unto them, nay threw open a wide gap to their familiarity, solas't each other in their low ungrac'd condition as Caius Marius and Carthage did of old in the Historian prayd together for the confusion of the Churches and Kingdomes glory.<note n="*" place="margin">Vellcius Paterculus.</note> Prerogative and Prelacy; indeed by Gods connivance in Processe of time, so it came to passe, that this mongrell monstrous beast begotten between a sectary and an envious Peere, so thrived and gathered strength whether thorough the novelty of the proiect (for the Vulgar are usualy ravished with new fangles) or the activity and zeale of these cursed incendiarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, who l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ft no stone unroll'd to bring about the designe; your Maiesti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Cathedrall subiects were put into a bodily feare, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir fatall period and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olation was drawing neere, and that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy (which I tremble to relate) was either to be devorsed from Prerogative, or else both as they had long stood, so in a trice were to fall together, and the glorious Church and Monarchy of England to run the same base fates with Democraticall Scotland. This unexpected hurl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-burly (as there was iust cause) soone put your Maiesties sacred Clergy out of these devout offices, which held the peoples hearts unto them, and we b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>came a sort of men cheap and contemptible, untill at length it pleased God by a new ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssion of Martiall vigour to strengthen your Maiesties sacred arme, and to rouse up the sleepie courage of your liege people, so farre that the greater and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ter part of your Kingdome, were animated to declare to fight for your maiesties rights (a large portion of which have no other fountaine then your Clergies height, and nearnesse to your Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) since which time (your Maiestie and we all can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but with exult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nowledge by the Cathedrall prayers of your Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as well as by the swords o th se sonn of Mars, the heroic Cavalier: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glorious victories have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n obtained, as at Keinton, Branford, Marlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Cirencester &amp; in the North: all which and the rest, which are yet to come are under God, wholly to be attributed to the speciall respect the Allmighty beares to your Most Religious Person, and to the Canonicall, Cathedrall Prayers of your upper Clergy, so that now your Maiesties, &amp; your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es glorie, seemes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly to havh been Eclipsed for a time that it migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t shine forth again in fulle strength, &amp; gaine new beams by that disconsolat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t after a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l these testimonies from heaven of the truth of your Maiesties cause, one particular there is, by the demerits whereof without early prevention we may chance to hazzard all our happinesse in the very haven, and that is it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155891:5"/> which with submission to your Majesties divine judgement I shall now take the boldnesse in a few words to discover, and it is none other then that most unhappy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident cast in of late, no doubt by the impure hand of Satan, nay to blast our bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nay almost flourishing hopes, that unparalelled profanation of Gods and your Majesties Churches, which I began to looke at, at the entrance of this my addresse to your Majesty, but was diverted and thrust aside by those uncivill justlers of Monarchy it selfe, whom I could not but for a time let flie at, even in the presence of your Majesty; returning therefore from whence I have so long digressed, I shall now by your Majesties pardon and patience, cloze this humble tender of my duty and conscience in a briefe representation of this horrid fact, and the inconveniences, or mischiefes; rather which either have already, or will in reason infallibly attend it. The fact such, that I feare those so effectuall <hi>Cathedrall</hi> orisons of your Clergy, without some spcciall miracle of mercy from heaven upon them, cannot expiate, and therefore the mischiefes which must attend, will correspond to the deserts of such a Cause, if a timely humiliation ward them not off from us; I cannot then (dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne) longer dissemble that, which is the joy and hope of your enemies, and a rasor upon the hearts of your most faithfull Subjects, That too well, and too far violation of two of our neighbour Churches here in <hi>Oxford,</hi> that of Saint <hi>Giles,</hi> and <hi>Maudlins</hi> Parish, into which your <hi>Provost Marshall</hi> (no doubt for want of other convenience, but that satisfies not) thrust that Rebellious crew which a late Victory brought from <hi>Cirencester:</hi> I have heard the like was done at <hi>Kingston,</hi> but I will not beleeve it, oh that no man knew or beleeved this, it is the best wish I can breathe out, next unto that, it hath not at all been done, but done it is, I would there were an Act of oblivion past upon it, at least I would we could as easily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the infamy of it, as it might have been prevented: Your Majesty I know is cleare and innocent from this great offence, may the punishment fall upon that head which first conceived it, and may your sacred Majesty be untoucht, better your Church, your Kingdome fall, then your sacred person feele but one twinge of the toothache: How loath me thinkes I am to speake out all, how officiously my fancy stirs my tongue to other matters, but my thoughts will not, out it must, lest it burst in the delivery; your Churches (gracious Soveraigne) your Church s are disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, defiled, become an abomination in the sight of heaven, your Churches only dedicated to heavenly uses, are made to serve the vilest offices. Neither the sacred Font, that fountaine of spirituall life, nor the blessed Altar, that heaven upon earth, where Christ vouchsafed us more then his spirituall presence, can say I am not pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, I am not vile and contemptible, can the enemy say lesse, where is now their God? Certainly he will say, what is become of that reverence, that prostration, that opinion of holinesse, used and said to be in Churches, was all that service but a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155891:6"/> frolicke, but a toy, but a scene made to serve the times, and Churchmens turnes, will the next course of serving God be thought other then another frolick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, a base accommodation to the times? Will your Reverend Fathers be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beleeved, when they shall gravely tell that too much reverence cannot be used in the house of God, where God hath a speciall residence, is more present then elsewhere in the world, who can with silence, with patience, see God himselfe put out of his pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, and not be Martyrs in the vindication of such Sacril dge? Were there not houses to be found in your Majesties territories capable of these miscreants, besides your Churches? Let me once speake with freedome to your Majesty, better had it been that these Rebels had yet remained unquelled, that these enemies of your Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had yet exalted themselves, then that your God should have been thus dishonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, better had it been to have fled before our enemies, then that our God should have been put to flight, and chased from amongst us, and that in time of need, when Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, nay more, Episcopacy is so boldly assaulted. I feare dread Soveraigne, I would this feare were groundlesse, that <hi>Wallers</hi> late Victories, and the consternati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Subjects, owe themselves to no other cause, then the profanation of these Churches, those enemies of your Crown and heaven, though no friends to Churches, were yet so modest, or so politicke, as not to adventure upon this way of incensing heaven, untill they saw Gods justice ingaged against your party in some notable stroke of vengeance, so religious they were, as not to be leaders in the crime: I have done, and my hearts desire it is, that future misfortunes makes not your Majesty too sensible of the truth of that which is the silence of others who better might have spoken, Command of conscience only bad me say,</p>
                  <closer>Vivat Rex Carolus.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Such a Homily as this would, whether you respect the flattery, the blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the superstition, or the spightfull excursions not amisse have suited with the grave managing of a <hi>Cathedrall</hi> beard, and I wonder that none of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t rout of <hi>Cathedrall</hi> fugitives which now embase the Court, had not remembred to bestow on his Majesty one cast of their wonted zeale in this argument, but the truth is, the bouncing of Guns, the prauncing of Horses, the ratling of Armes, the pledging of healths, and the cursing of Schismaticks and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have disfurnished our <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Droanes of all thoughts of the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Churches; alas, when Episcopacy it selfe is so fiercely struck at, nay wounded in a vitall part, can a Bishop have the leasure, in such a time when all thoughts and industry is too little in seeking plaisters for the wounds of Episcopacy, to trouble and distract his minde about the service of God, and holinesse of Churches; indeed in a time of deep peace was seasonable for such thoughts, a time hewne out for the advancement of Churches and Churchmens
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155891:6"/> pomp, was how indiscreetly allowed to the ungratiating of Churches both with King and People: but the depth of <hi>Cathedrall</hi> miseries now it is, that it can only be said, such times lately were, when the wheele of Fortune is turned, and the robustious souldier sits uppermost, and at the next whirle the inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Seperatist may chance to peek up, <hi>Cathedrall</hi> men may commendably leave off tithing Mint and Cummin, leave off talking of Altars, and holinesse of Churches, and sadly meditate on those weightier matters, of maintaining wives and children, of securing their Carkases from the Parliaments Hawkes, and their houses from that terrible word <hi>Plunder:</hi> Me thinkes I heare a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall</hi> Humble. Bee buzzing out some such dolefull straines as these, Oh that there had been so much providence in our Velvet Nodles, as to have thought there might have been a Parliament, and such shrewd heads in it, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Grace of a King cannot purchase such as can overmatch them, which yet seemes very strange, especially since such care was taken to bring idlenesse and licentiousnesse in fashion both at the Innes of Court, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities, so that it had been (one would thinke) an easie matter for a Prince, in whose hand was the staple of all preferments, to have had choise of instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for any service, especially by the concurrent assistance of the Law and the Gospell, but yet which way soever it came about, improvident we were, and irrespective of afterclaps, else we might have laid up friends in <hi>Banke,</hi> even amongst the Seperatists themselves, which now would have besteed us in time of need, somwhat in prudence might have been abated in the rigorous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>action of Ceremonies, the Canons in force might have been executed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out spightfulnesse and delight, in the punishment of such as were found tardy, Churches might have been adorned like Matrons, not tricked up like strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, like the Idolatrous Temples of Rome, enough might have been done to draw on devotion, though all had been omitted which served to erect a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton love to Churches, it might hnve been said, and scarse gainsaid, that Churches were fitly both raised and used for the publike service of God, it needed not to have been added an unexpressable holinesse was impressed on the walls, by meanes of consecration, and then if an urgent necessity, as since hath happened (but then I beleeve had never been) had turned a Church into a Prison, it might fairely have been said, that Church had lost its use, not lost that holinesse it never had, and then this vile practise of the Cavaleers had not thus stuck like a bur of infamy in our Cathedrall throates, shall I say, or upon our consciences, if any such thing we have hardlier to be removed then taking up Armes against our Prince, from the tender Conscience of an honest Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist, neither then (say I) had there been occasion to have raised or resolved
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155891:7"/> these two questions mentioned in the frontispeece, which in the last place call for a dispatch, and the first was this:</p>
            <p rend="indent">Quest. <hi>Whether the Seperatist (as he is called) who makes his house, or (as it is said) his Barne a Church, be more scandalous, or the Cavalier (who look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another way in his discourse and profession) hath at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where his Majestie resides, turned Churches (with reverence be it spoken) into prisons, and Jakes, and in <hi>Devon,</hi> at many places into Stables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Question seemes to be, and is, I beleeve, in some mens apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a Case of Conscience, yet, I feare me, little will be contributed either from the Popish, or Protestant Casuists towards the decision▪ for, as I guesse, they have not heard of it, much lesse handled it; neverthelesse feare not, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader, but that it may be fairely determined, for I have heard a wise man say, that a tollerable understanding best states a point of Conscience, when there is least of these Casuists both directions and judgements in it. Give me leave first to explaine some things in the Question, and then thou shalt have my iudgement, such as it is, in this weighty matter. First then, by the Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist I meane all those people of new or old <hi>England,</hi> who either will not, or else have no great heart to ioyne in the outward worship of God, with any, be their learning or esteeme what it will, who make a conscience of Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call policy, or Discipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it was lately mannaged by the Archbishops, Bishops, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, I adde that Parenthesis <hi>(as they are called)</hi> to imply that in my judgement, though they are usually so called by the adverse party, yet they are ill called Seperatists, for (good men) they agree throughout with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Protestant, in the maine of Gods worship, and in the whole Doctrine of the Gospell, but Seperatist only in that, wherein they are in conscience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded they ought not, and the adverse party cannot, in the judgement of any indifferent man convince them, that they ought to joyne unto them: Indeed when it shall be made cleare, or certaine, that they ought to joyne with the <hi>Cathedrall</hi> party, and then they shall stand off, I also shall be well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have them Christened Seperatists.</p>
            <p>In the meane time I wonder that any, at least iudicious men, should fasten a terme of disgrace (for so it is accounted) upon men both upright in their lives, and Orthodox in their tenets, meerly for not according with them in a humour, for not complying in a point of outward uniformity, when variety (for ought hath beene said to the contrary) hath both as much decency, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155891:7"/> might have for its companion, as much charity, in my poore iudgement (which I professe in Gods sight is impreiudiced for ought I know in this cause) men may as well call him a Seperatist, that betakes himselfe from one neighbourhood to another, or from one Corporation to another; for as such a man may be as good a Subiect to his King in both places, though hee observe not the same Customes, and should be accounted so; in like manner the other whom heedlesse men call a Seperatist, keeping the Relation to God, and his people inviolable, so farre as God Commands him, at least sincerely indeavouring it, is capable of, and should have our Charitie, and good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (though he differed from us in these outward Ceremonies) as cordially, as he that most of all complies with us, nay, more many times, if reason may be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard, for many agree with the <hi>Cathedrall men</hi> meerely out of fashion, and this man differs out of conscience, and what man, who is sound in the Head-peece, likes not a man better than a <hi>Jacke-an-Apes,</hi> at least each wiseman should doe so.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, when, I say, [<hi>That the Seperatist makes his house</hi> or (as its said) <hi>his Barne a Church</hi>] I speake it againe in the words of his Calumniators, for it hath not yet beene made apparent that he doth either, at least, not the latter, how ever it is not their constant opinion (who beare that name) that Churches should be disus'd, and Barnes, or private Houses serve in stead of Churches, onely this much is true, that in regard they are offended at the Customes and humane impositions in our publike worship, they chuse rather to serve God in their private houses, or it may be any where, then omit the performance of so necessary a duty, so that what they now doe is onely <hi>In casu necessitatis,</hi> and whilst our publike places of worship are not open, at least, for the foppish Ceremonies used in them are offensive to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, the burthen of the <hi>Quere</hi> resting upon these words <hi>[More scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous]</hi> It is but convenient that this phrase of comparison be well weighed: First then, I would not have any man hence inferre, that the practise of the Seperatist is at all scandalous in propriety of speech, because I am about to prove the practise of the Cavaliers is more scandalous, for the scandall which ariseth from the practise of the <hi>Nonconformist</hi> (for so may he most fitly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, unlesse you please to call him, what in very truth he is, an honest man,) is only <hi>Scandalum acceptum,</hi> a positive Scandall, a scandall in fancie and opinion only, wheras that of the Cavalier is <hi>Scandalum datum</hi> an active scandall, a scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall in truth and reallity: Secondly, I would thus be conceiv'd that to any man that makes a conscience of his ways, the Practise of the Cavaliers upon suppt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of their owne principles touching the holinesse of Churches, which yo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155891:8"/> the Seperatist conceives and that truely, most false is, at least ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted more offensive, even to the men of their own party, as having in it a just cause of scandall then the practise of the Non-conformists; suppose all true which is obiected can be either to the Cavalier, or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hristi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the former being truely scandalous, the latter in a grondolesse opinion onely, and therefore the former is more scandalous; neverthelesse leaving the indifferent Reader to his owne judgement touching what is scandalous, or more scandalous, I shall, I doubt not, by the Reasons following make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>ad hominem,</hi> at least that the practise of the Cavalier is most scandalous, and that out of the notorious Position of their owne party.</p>
            <p>First, then one point of their Divinity is, that Irreverence in Churches is scandalous upon this ground; they condemne all such as bow not at the Name of <hi>Jesus;</hi> all such as receive not the blessed Sacrament Kneeling, all such as bow not at the Altar, or stand not up at <hi>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</hi> as scandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, whence I subsume, that if these men are upon these titles scandalous, then <hi>a fortiori,</hi> much more the Cavaliers, who by dishonouring, by polluting, and unhallowing whole Churches, at once casheeres all those observances, the very neglect whereof in others they cry up as scandalous.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, another principle of theirs is, That throwing downe of Organs, silencing of Cathedrall Roarers and Squeakers, overturning of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls, battering of Paint and Images, pulling up railes, assaulting of Surpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Common-Prayer-Bookes is scandalous, whence I likewise inferre <hi>a fortiori,</hi> that thus violating of whole Churches, and prophaning and unhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing all the sacred Utensils of Churches is much more scandalous, which is the knowne gracious practises of the holy Cavaliers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Position of theirs is, that by vertue of Consecration there is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed an holinesse on Churches, and therefore such as unhallow them in any kinde are eminently scandalous, yet the Cavalier (whose Doctrine this is) notwithstanding this holinesse of Churches, converts Churches into Stables, Prisons, Jakes, a worser unhallownesse then which cannot be immagined, unlesse the Cavaliers themselves quartered in Churches, and by their blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Oathes, Execrations, ribaldry, made their Church (which their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science would not startle at) their hell.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, and lastly, they Voted unanimously that the Seperatist, who makes his House or Barne a Church is truely scandalous, and if so, then let any man of conscience or judgement, tell me whether the Cavalier be not much more scandalous, who in stead of making his House and Barne a Church, transformes his Church to what was said before. That this last Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155891:8"/> may have (as its fit) its full weight and emphasis, consider with me (good Reader) for a short time;</p>
            <p>First, the Fact of the Seperatist with the aggravations of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Fact of the Cavaliers and its aggravation.</p>
            <p>And then by an equall ballancing or comparing them together, any man may easily discerne whether of the twaine is more impious and scandalous, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tist or the Cavalier.</p>
            <p>For the first, the Separatists Fact is, that he makes his House or Barne a Church, for let that also for once be admitted, which yet hath not beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but by Fame, which is usually a Lyer, nor what it is to make an House or Barne a Church? and wherein lies the hainousnesse and offence of him that doth so? I answer, to make a private House or Barne a Church, is either to doe the Offices which are proper to a Church, or to allow the Offices which are proper to a Church to be done in a private House or Barne; what these Officers are, those of the Cavaliers who come to Church connot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of, and they are chiefely; 1. Preaching or Expounding the Scriptures. 2. Administring the Sacraments; unto which you may adde, if you please, as secondary things; 1. Prayer. Secondly, Marriage. Thirdly, Burying, and then either all, or most, or some at least of these must be done by the Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, or any other that makes his House or Barne a Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the aggravation or crime of the Seperatists fact is this. 1. That he <hi>[the Seperatist]</hi> who possibly, or probably, or certainly is not in holy orders, that is, hath not been sanctified by any Bishops sacred Clutch, now appointed solemnly to the performance of such holy duties, yet usurpes and dares to doe the office of him, that hath been thus consecrated or hallowed unto them. 2. That he the Seperatist, a layman, and not of the Clergy, dares doe these offices in a private house, or which is more, in a barne, in the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Rats and Mice, which should only be done. 1. By Clergy men. 2. In consecrated hollowed places. 3. His fact is aggravated by the Law which hee violates in so doing, which is first the Statute Law of the Laud, as they say, Secondly, The Laws and constitutions of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Thirdly, the Canon Law, of the Popes Law (which <hi>Luther</hi> called <hi>mendam Papalem</hi>) and which yet sticks upon, and layes hold on us, where it is not against the Lawes of God, or of the Land; as they say, Fourthly, his fact is further ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated, 1. By the time, for he is generally said to doe these offices at an uncanonicall time, as in the night, or when he lists, when the Spirit (as the Cavaliere Phrases it sweetly) moves him. 2. By the manner of doing it, which is, they say, 1. In spight and opposition to the Hierarchie. 2. Without these holy weeds, and customes of Vestments, as Surplice, Cap, Cope, Crosier,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155891:9"/> Rochet, Gowne, Canonicall Coat, consecrated slippers, without cringings, prostrations, stations, or conversions to the East. 5. All this he doth out of conscience, and full perswasion that what he doth is more acceptable to God. And are not these, my friend, haynous things, and unsufferable in a Church, and Christian commonwealth, and offensive to all that heare of, and see it?</p>
            <p>In the next place consider with me the fact of the Cavaleer, with its aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p>His fact is, that he converts the Churches of God into Barnes, Stables, Jakes, that is, he either doth himselfe, or causeth to be done (which is not an haires bredth to chuse) the same offices in Churches which are proper to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Stables, Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. And now heare the aggravation of his fact: He <hi>[The Cavalier]</hi> who maintain that Churches are not to be defiled, who holds that there is an holinesse in Churches, who condemne, and would gladly destroy the Seperatist for his rudenesse even toward Church-implements, he the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part, nay the totall of whose devotion and religion it is to have God alone served in Churches, and with those Ceremonies which the Seperatist abhors, in short, he who had rather be a Papist, then part with such ceremonies. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, yet he <hi>[The Cavaleer]</hi> not only unhallows the Utensils of Churches, but profanes the Churches themselves, and for the manner and measure as bad, if not worse then the <hi>Goth,</hi> or <hi>Turke,</hi> for can a <hi>Turke</hi> or <hi>Goth</hi> doe more vilely then make a stable or jakes of a Church? Thirdly, his fact is aggravated by the time, and what is the time when the Cavaleer doth thus dishonour Churches? even when he fights to maintaine the honour of Churches, when he kils the Seperatist for tampering with something in Churches. Fourthly, He doth all this where his Maiesty resides, in an University, in the sight of the Reverend clergy, who have so constantly preached and written in the defence of the holinesse of Churches. Nay, fifthly, he is not only content to doe, and approve, and applaud this vile fact himselfe, but hath likewise corrupted the judgements of the grave Fathers of our Church, hath drawne them into the society of this crime, he hath got the lights of our Church to legitimate his black impiety. Sixthly, by his fact he hath violated all the Laws, and Canons in this behalfe like an arrant Seperatist. And lastly, all this he hath done, even whilest he is throughly resolved, and perswaded in conscience, that he ought to have done the contrary, nay when he knew that all his party are scandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the rudenesse of the Sep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ratist, which yet is not to be named the same day with this prodious <hi>Gothique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (my friend) what thinkest thou, how many bowes short is the Cavaleer off the sin against the Holy Ghost?</p>
            <p>In the last place, let us ponder and ballance (as I promised to doe) these facts thus qualified as you have heard.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:155891:9"/>
            <p>First, then the Seperatist offends out of sillinesse and ignorance, and at least pretendeth conscience for what he doth, but the Cavalier in regard of his wisdome and knowledge doth all this even against conscience. Secondly, the Seperatist by his rudenesse offends onely the Cavalier his mortall enemy, but the Cavalier his owne party, his friends of whom he should be most ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Thirdly, The Sepreatist is offensive onely for not joyning with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier in some outward, and as the Seperatist is perswaded an indifferent part of Gods Worship, but the Cavaliers in that which he judgeth most necessary.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Seperatist is offensive for running in Common with the Cavalier, but the Cavalier takes in horses, and lets them runne in Common with the Groomes in Gods House, as at <hi>Kingston, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Saperatist cannot be perswaded that he violates any Law of God or man, but the Cavalier knowes that he violates all Lawes.</p>
            <p>Lastly, the Seperatist is frequent in the service of God at home, and at Church he will heare Sermons, but the Cavalier serves the devill at home, and his revenge and his horses at Church; and now let my Cavalier, who is not drunke or mad (if any such may be found) judge whether is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and scandalous, He, or the Seperatist.</p>
            <p>How gladly would I learne what the most profound Cathedrall Doctor in <hi>Oxford</hi> could Answer to these Reasons, what evasions they could excogitate, for reconciling the practise of their Patrons with their acknowledged Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But alas! what reason hath any man at this time, of all times, to expect sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties from <hi>Oxford,</hi> where before the King came thither, when Sacke aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Tavernes, the height of judgement was but some frothy <hi>Nonscence</hi> raptures of wit, but since (God knowes) by reason of that long unhappy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce betweene their braines and the spirit of Sacke, nothing hath flow'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the sad complexion of dull Ale, and Colledge Taplash.</p>
            <p>Neverthelesse though I utterly despaire of satisfaction from them, I will be so courteous as to lend them a word of Counsell, and to wish them capable of it, and it is this: That since the world is so offended with this beastly fact of their Minions, and disappointed of all just and reasonable Apologies for it, from themselves, they would exhort very earnestly the Cavaliers, and others whom it may concerne, to play an after-game of Repentance and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, so that at least they might skin over that wound which they cannot heale.</p>
            <p>The Church Story not impertinently to this purpose, makes mention of a <hi>Morussian</hi> Prince (as I remember) called <hi>Cabares,</hi> who pursuing the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandalls</hi> with an huge Army, still in his passage as he went, cleansed all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155891:10"/> those Churches, which that impure Nation had defil'd; and would it not be an exemplary peece of piety, and much tending to the honour of your party with posterity? First, if the Cavaliers would in their hands, or mouthes, or any other more fitting way carry out the filth of those Churches, which by a more than <hi>Gothish</hi> impiety they have defiled; and then secondly, if the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cleargy would humble themselves so low as to come after the Cavaliers, and with their Cathedrall Beesome-like Beards sweepe them; and so much be spoken touching our first Question: the second was,</p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi>Whether Churches thus prophaned, and fallen from Grace and holinesse are not by the Bishops to be consecrated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which Question with all manner of expedition: First then the Puritans here, so much he is for holinesse, would, I warrant you, goe neare to hold they ought, if he thought,</p>
            <p n="1">1. First, That there were no neede of consecrating Churches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, that any holinesse were stampt on Churches by the Ministry of Consecration.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And thirdly, that Churches could fall from Grace or holinesse, once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but holding neither of these, its probable that his iudgement stands for the negative.</p>
            <p>Secondly, on the other side the <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Doctors maintaining with one consent; 1. A necessity of Consecrating Churches. 2. Undiscernable Characters of holinesse impressed on Churches. 3. Falling from Grace in the best Saints of God, much more inanimate Churches must in reason be thought to hold the affirmative, and that Churches thus defiled ought to be reconsecrated, especially considering,</p>
            <p>First, That Consecration of Churches is an holy and heavenly Work, which begets an high and reverend esteeme in the people; for say the people, the Bishops must needs be eminently holy men, who can make dead Churches holy, and therefore at this time when Bishops have beene much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, all occasions should be catcht at, for a reingendring in the people a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiall conceit of these holy Fathers; and therefore reconsecration not to be past by.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Considering that it may chance to be scandalous, and to their brethren of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not to have these unhallowed Churches (though in pollicie made so at their instigation) reconsecrated, of whose con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences they ought to be very tender, in requitall of their bowells of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion towards the Bishops cause lately in much ieopardy to have beene
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155891:10"/> consumed by the fiery zeale of the Schismaticks, had not that holy man of <hi>Rome</hi> and his agents be stirred their stumps, and brought more than holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the extinguishing of that flame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, considering that the Consecration of a Church, which is no great labour, and brings no benefit at all, either to Auditors or spectators (which is at length to be thought on, least the People by the Bishops meanes grow too Holy, and too knowing, as of late it fell out, both to their shame and smart) will save the good Father a Sermon for that weeke of Consecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is well saved, especially since experience hath atught the Church of late, that Sermons have done so much mischeefe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, considering that at the reconsecrating of every Church, there ought to be a consecration Dinner at the charge of the Parish, which will be comfortable both to his Lordships old corps and no false Latin in his purse by saving a meale after these hard pinching times, which had almost exhausted all, and <hi>tantum non,</hi> brought <hi>rem ad repem,</hi> that is, brought his good Lordship within a close or two off the Beggar.</p>
            <p>Lastly, considering that so few Churches are in these peevish times erected, and therfore though there be no great need (supposing Churches cleansed and swept as was above advised) of reconsecration of them, yet least the holy Father should forget the trick of it, and so the Country People, in case there be at any time an occasion of consecration, and the boyes shoud have matter ministred unto them to laugh at his Lordship, when possible he should be (through disuse) to seeke what to doe next.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding all these strong reasons for the reconsecration of Churches, it seemes not onely expedient but necessary not to reconsecrate them. 1. In case the Kings Maiestie or the Queen, or the Privy Councell, or the Chiefe Prelate then in highest place, do not approve it. 2. In case there can be no consecration dinner, or a poore one. 3. In case the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> declare to the contrary. and Lastly, in case his Lordship be decrepit, and cannot trample about all the time without danger of having a fit of the gout, or stone, and then it shall be thought sufficent that his Lordship either omit the duty, or consecrate onely the new Boards, Poasts or other Utensills, which were not before consecrated, that so a greater good may be consulted. <hi>viz:</hi> his good Lordships ease, and indeed were I freely to give my Judgment, this much (if any thing at all were to be done) would be enough, for my private opinion it is (gentle Reader pardon me that I tell not from whence I had it, untill I know my Authors pleasure from whom I had it, whether I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale it) that consecration is a kinde of Baptisme, and therefore should not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155891:11"/> be iterated, least wee simbolize too farr with the cursed Anabaptist, and therefore onely the new parts of a Church should be consecrated, no part reconsecrated, and yet in this new way there are new difficulties, not a few, as if Consecration be a kind of Baptisme, why should not a man, who hath beene Baptized in his infancy, be rebaptized when he is growne a greate Lubber, and hath gotten much new flesh about him, as well as a Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive consecration in the new parts of it; and many more such difficulties I could with more ease conjure up then put them downe againe, but I beleeve such are niceties, which a man may be ignorant of, or else Holy Church will hereafter resolve them, if we can have the patience to waite her leasure, and so I shake hands with this perplexed Case touching the reconsecration of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed Churches.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>